<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a goodly treatyse, and it is called, A notable lesson, otherwyse it is called The golden pystle</title>
            <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1530</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S664</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22152650</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22152650</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08836)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2248:5, 1762:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a goodly treatyse, and it is called, A notable lesson, otherwyse it is called The golden pystle</title>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
                  <author>Bernard, of Clairvaux, Saint, 1090 or 91-1153. Epistola de perfectione vitae.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Impry[n]ted by me Wynkyn de Worde, dwellynge in London, in Flete strete, at the sygne of the Sonne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the xxiii daye of Noue[m]ber, in [the] yere of our Lorde God, M.CCCCC. and xxx. [23 Nov. 1530]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"This was brought vnto me in Englysshe of an olde translacyon rugh, and rude, and requyred to amende it. I thought lesse labour to wryte newe the whole ..." signed: Rycharde Whytforde--P. [7].</note>
                  <note>An adaptation, by Richard Whitford, of Bernard's Epistola de perfectione vitae--Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>T.p. contains woodcut illustration.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Exeter College (University of Oxford). Library (reel 1762:25), and Folger Shakespeare Library (reel 2248:5).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:1"/>
            <p>¶Here begynneth a goodly treatyſe / and it is called / a notable leſſon / otherwyſe it is called the golden pyſtle. Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſus. Anno domini. M.CCCCC.xxx.</p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good / holſome leſſon &amp; profytable vnto al chryſtianes / aſcrybed vnto ſaynt Bernarde / and put amonge his werkes [I thynke] by ſome good man / that wolde it ſhulde therby haue the more authoryte / and the rather be redde / and better be borne away. For doubtles it is a good mater / and edificatyue vnto all them that haue a zele / and cure vnto ſoule helthe &amp; deſyre of ſaluacyon. It is called in the tytle. Notabile docume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum. that is to ſay / a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leſſon. And ſome done call it the golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. It foloweth immedyately after a lytell werke called Formula honeſte vite. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme / and maner of an honeſt lyfe / or of honeſt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F you intende to pleaſe god / and wolde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne grace to fulfyll the ſame / two thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ben vnto you very neceſſary. The fyrſt. You muſt withdrawe your mynde from all worldly &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſytory thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / in ſuche maner / as though you cared not wheder any ſuche thynges were in this worlde / or no. The ſecunde is. That you gyue and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply youre ſelfe ſo wholy to god / and haue youre ſelfe in ſuche a wayte / that you neuer do / ſay / ne thynke / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you knowe / ſuppoſe / or byleue ſhulde offende or dyſpleaſe god / for by this meane / you may ſoneſt and moſt redely obtayne / and wynne his fauour and grace. In all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges eſteme and acount your ſelfe moſt vyle / &amp; moſt ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / and as very nought in reſpecte / and regarde of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue / and thynke / ſuppoſe / &amp; byleue that all perſones ben good / &amp; better than you be / for ſo ſhall you moche pleaſe our lorde. What ſo euer you ſe / or ſeme to ꝑecyue / in any perſon / or yet here of any chryſtyane / take you none occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion therin / but rather aſcrybe / &amp; apply you all vnto the beſt / &amp; thynke or ſuppoſe / all is done or ſayde for a good intent / or purpoſe / though it ſeme contrary. For mannes ſuſpicions and lyght iudgmentes ben ſoone / and lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceyued / or begyled. Dyſpleaſe no perſon wyllyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Ne euer ſpeke euyll of any perſon / though it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſay. For it is not lawfull to ſhewe in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyce / or defaute of any ꝑſon / excepte you myght otherwyſe ſhewe &amp; declare your owne offence. Speke lytell or nought vnto your ꝓpre / &amp; ſelfe laude / or prayſe / thoughe it were true / and vnto your famylyer felowe / or feythfull fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. But ſtudy to kepe ſecrete / and pryuey your vertue / rather than your vyce. Yet were it a cruell dede for any ꝑſons to defame them ſelfe. Be more gladde
<pb facs="tcp:25186:3"/>
to gyue your eare / &amp; herynge vnto the prayſe / rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the dyſprayſe of any perſon. And euer byware as well of herynge / as ſpekynge of detraccyon. And whan you ſpeke / take good deliberacion / &amp; haue fewe wordes / &amp; let thoſe be true / and good: ſadly ſet &amp; wyſely ordred. Yf any wordes be ſpoken vnto you of vyce / or vanyte (as ſoone as you may) breke of / &amp; leue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talke / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And euer returne / and apply your ſelfe vnto ſome appoynted good / &amp; godly occupacyon / bodyly / or ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Yf any ſoden chaunce fall or happe vnto you / or vnto any of youres / leyne not to lyghtly ther vnto / ne care moch therfore. Yf it be of ꝓſperite / reioyce not moch ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in / ne be ouer glad therof. Yf it be aduerſite / be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt / or ouerthrowen therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / ne brought to ſorowe / or ſad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / thanke god of all / &amp; ſet lytle therby. Repute all thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges tranſytorye: as of lytle pryce or valure. Gyue euer moſt thought / &amp; care vnto thoſe thynges / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may profyte &amp; promote y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. Fle / &amp; auoyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſones / &amp; places of moche ſpeche / for better is to kepe ſcyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / than to ſpeke. Kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tymes &amp; places of ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce precyſely / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſpeke not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out reaſonable &amp; vnfeyned cauſe. The tymes of ſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in religion be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe. From collacion vnto maſſe be en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of terce. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt grace i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fraytour / vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later grace. And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge of eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> long / vnto grace be ended after ſouꝑ / or els En<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicite / af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune bouer. The places of ſcile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / ben: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clauſtre / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fraytour &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dortour. Yf you ye ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred / &amp; done take occaſyon at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faute / or offence of any perſon / than loke well vpon youre ſelfe / wheder you be in the ſame defaute ſumtyme your ſelfe / &amp; than haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion vpon your brother / or ſyſter. Yf ther be none ſuche defaut in you / thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke verely / &amp; byleue / ther may be / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do: as
<pb facs="tcp:25186:3"/>
done ſoone fade / and fle for euer. The good perſones / for theyr troubles ſuffred here vpon erthe: done get &amp; wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne eterne &amp; euerlaſtynge glorye / whiche the euyll perſones done loſe. And contrary theſe euyll / &amp; ſynfull perſones / for theyr ioy &amp; pleaſures here / done reyue by exchaunge eterne &amp; euerlaſtynge ſhame / &amp; rebuke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peyne / &amp; wo vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpecable. Whan ſo euer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ben dyſpoſed to ſlugyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / or to be drowſy / remyſſe in prayer / or dull in deuocy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take this lytle werke / or ſome other good treaty / &amp; rede therin / &amp; euer note well the contentes therof / and what is ment therby. And yf you be not therby delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or eaſed therof / than ſhyfte vnto ſome other werke / or occupacyon / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer you auoyde ydlenes / &amp; al vayne paſtymes / whiche in dede ben loſe tyme. And than reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre that thoſe that nowe byde in peyne / other in hell / or yet in purgagory for ſuche tymes ſo paſſed / or loſt / had leuer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / haue ſuche tyme to redeme theyr peynes by / as you may haue yf you wyl. Tyme tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to al ꝑſones wel ocupied / is veray precious / &amp; dere. By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware well therfore: how you ſpende it / or paſſe it. For you can neuer reuoke it / nor call it bakke. Yf the tyme paſſe you by trouble / &amp; vexacyon / thynke they ben hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py / and gracyous that ben paſt this wretched lyfe / and nowe in blys / for they ſhall neuer haue any ſuche miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. And whan you fele a conforde or conſolacyon ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall / thanke god therof / &amp; thynke the dampned ſoules ſhall neuer haue any ſuche pleaſure. And thus let this be for your exercyſe in the datyue. At nyght whan you go reſt / fyrſt make a counte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ſelfe / &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre how you haue ſpende / or paſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day &amp; tyme / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was gyuen you to be vſed in vertue / &amp; how you haue byſtowed your thoughtes / your wordes / and your werkes. And yf you
<pb facs="tcp:25186:4"/>
fynde no great thynge amys / gyue the whole laud and prayſe vnto our lorde god. And yf you perceyue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary / that you haue myſſpende any parte therof / be ſory ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / and byſeche our lorde of mercy / and forgyueneſſe / &amp; promyſe and verely purpoſe to make amendes the nexte day. And yf you haue portunyte ther vpon / it ſhalbe full conuenyent for you to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed on the nexte morowe. And ſpecyally yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater done / ſayde / or thought by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate conſent / do greuouſly wey / &amp; worke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a grudge in your conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: than wolde I aduyſe you neuer to ete nor drynke / tyll you be dyſcharged therof / yf you may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenyently get a ghoſtly father. Now for a concluſyon of this werke / put byfore you / as by caſe or ymaginacyon. ij. large cytyes / one full of trouble / turmoyle / and myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye / and let that be hell. The other cyte full of ioye / glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / conforte / and pleaſure / and let that be heuen. Loke well on them bothe / for in bothe be many dwellers / and great compeny. Then caſt and thynke within your ſelfe what thynge here myght ſo pleaſe you that you ſhulde chuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wors cyte / or what thynge ſhulde dyſpleaſe you on the other parte / wherby you ſhulde withdrawe your ſelfe from that vertue that myght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaye &amp; brynge you vnto the other cyte. And whan you haue ſtudyed well here vpon / and can nothynge fynde / I dare well aſſure you yf you kepe well the preceptes and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyles of this lytle leſſon / you ſhall fynde the ryght way / for the holy ghoſt wyll inſtructe / &amp; teche you where you be not ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent of your ſelfe / ſo you endeuoyre &amp; gyue dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / to bere away &amp; to folowe that here is taught. Rede it euery weke ones / or twyſe / or oftener yf you wyll. And where you profyte / gyue thankes / laude / and prayſe vnto oure lorde god / &amp; moſt ſwete ſauyour Ieſu chryſt / who ſende
<pb facs="tcp:25186:4"/>
you his mercy and grace / that alway lyueth god. In ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula ſeculorum. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_note">
            <p>¶This was brought vnto me in englyſſhe of an olde tranſlacyon rugh / and rude / and requyred to amende it. I thought leſſe labour to wryte newe the whole / and I haue done vnto the ſentence not very nere the letter / and in dyuers places added ſome thynges folowynge vpon the ſame to make the mater more ſentencyous / and full. I byſeche you take all vnto the beſt / and praye for the olde wretched brother of Syon Rychatde Whytforde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Impry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by me Wynkyn de Worde / dwellynge in London / in Flete ſtrete / at the ſygne of the Sonne. The .xxiij. daye of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our lorde god .M.CCCCC. and .xxx.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <head>wynkyn de worde.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25186:6"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
